Luciano Marchezan, MSc.

☑ lucianomarchp@gmail.com

in @lucianomarchezan

https://lucianomarchezan.github.io/



Summary

Has experience in Computer Science, focusing on Software Engineering.

Graduated as Software Engineer at Universidade Federal do Pampa (UNIPAMPA) - Campus Alegrete. Obtained the Ph.D. diploma at the Institute of Software Systems Engineering (ISSE) at the Johannes Kepler University (JKU), supervised by Prof. Dr. Alexander Egyed. Finished Master Degree in Software Engineering at Universidade Federal do Pampa - Campus Alegrete in 2020. Worked for 5 years at the Laboratory of Empirical Studies in Software Engineering (LESSE) as a researcher on the topics of Software Product Lines with a focus on Re-engineering.

Currently, a Post Doctoral Researcher at the Institute of Software Systems Engineering (ISSE) at Johannes Kepler University Austria. The current research includes Model-Driven Software Engineering, Automated Software Engineering, Software Reuse, and Empirical Software Engineering

Employment History

2020 - · · · ·	University Assistant/Researcher - Institute of Software Systems Engineering - Johannes
	Kepler University, Linz, Austria
2019 – 2020	Full Stack Developer - Capataz, Sustainable Livestock, Alegrete RS - Brazil.
	Full Stack Developer - EletroVirtual, Alegrete RS - Brazil.
2017 - 2017	Full Stack Developer - Porthal Sistemas, Alegrete RS - Brazil.
2014 - 2014	Front End Developer - GreenWays2Go, Chigao IL - USA.

Education

2021 - 2023	Ph.D. Computer Science (ongoing) at Johannes Kepler University, Linz, Austria.
	Thesis title: Improving Consistency Maintenance for Collaborative Software Systems Engineering.
2019 – 2020	M.Sc. Software Engineering, at Universidade Federal do Pampa, Alegrete, Brazil. Thesis title: <i>PAxSPL: A generic framework to support the planning of SPL reengineering.</i>
2012 - 2018	B.Sc. Software Engineering, at Universidade Federal do Pampa, Alegrete, Brazil. Thesis title: <i>PAxSPL: a Feature Retrieval Process for Software Product Line Re-engineering.</i>

Research Publications

Journal Articles

- L. Marchezan, R. Kretschmer, W. Assunção, A. Reder, and A. Egyed, "Generating repairs for inconsistent models," *Software and Systems Modeling*, 2022, ISSN: 16191374. ODOI: 10.1007/s10270-022-00996-0.
- L. Marchezan, E. Rodrigues, W. Assunção, M. Bernardino, F. Basso, and J. Carbonell, "Software product line scoping: A systematic literature review," *Journal of Systems and Software*, vol. 186, 2022, ISSN: 01641212. ODI: 10.1016/j.jss.2021.111189.
- M. Tröls, L. Marchezan, A. Mashkoor, and A. Egyed, "Instant and global consistency checking during collaborative engineering," *Software and Systems Modeling*, vol. 21, 6 2022, ISSN: 16191374. ODOI: 10.1007/s10270-022-00984-4.

- A. Iung, J. Carbonell, L. Marchezan, et al., "Systematic mapping study on domain-specific language development tools," *Empirical Software Engineering*, vol. 25, 5 2020, ISSN: 15737616. ODOI: 10.1007/s10664-020-09872-1.
- L. Marchezan, E. M. Rodrigues, M. Bernardino, and F. P. Basso, "PAxSPL: A feature retrieval process for software product line reengineering," *Software Practice and Experience*, vol. 49, 8 2019, ISSN: 1097024X. DOI: 10.1002/spe.2707.
- M. Bernardino, E. Rodrigues, A. Zorzo, and L. Marchezan, "Systematic mapping study on mbt: Tools and models," *IET Software*, vol. 11, 4 2017, ISSN: 17518806. ODOI: 10.1049/iet-sen.2015.0154.

Conference Proceedings

- E. Herac, W. Assunção, L. Marchezan, R. Haas, and A. Egyed, "A flexible operation-based infrastructure for collaborative model-driven engineering," 2, The 19th European Conference on Modelling Foundations and Applications (ECMFA 2023), vol. 22, Jul. 2023, 2:1–14. ODOI: 10.5381/jot.2023.22.2.a5.
- L. Marchezan, W. K. G. Assunção, E. Herac, F. Keplinger, A. Egyed, and C. Lauwerys, "Fulfilling industrial needs for consistency among engineering artifacts," in 2023 IEEE/ACM 45th International Conference on Software Engineering: Software Engineering in Practice (ICSE-SEIP), 2023, pp. 246–257.

 DOI: 10.1109/ICSE-SEIP58684.2023.00028.
- L. Marchezan, W. K. G. Assunção, G. K. Michelon, and A. Egyed, "Do developers benefit from recommendations when repairing inconsistent design models? a controlled experiment," in *Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on Evaluation and Assessment in Software Engineering*, ser. EASE '23, Oulu, Finland: Association for Computing Machinery, 2023, pp. 131–140, ISBN: 9798400700446. DOI: 10.1145/3593434.3593482.
- L. Marchezan, W. K. G. Assuncao, R. Kretschmer, and A. Egyed, "Change-oriented repair propagation," in Proceedings of the International Conference on Software and System Processes and International Conference on Global Software Engineering, ser. ICSSP'22, Pittsburgh, PA, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, 2022, pp. 82–92, ISBN: 9781450396745. ODI: 10.1145/3529320.3529330.
- L. Marchezan, W. K. G. Assunção, G. Michelon, E. Herac, and A. Egyed, "Code smell analysis in cloned java variants: The apo-games case study," in *Proceedings of the 26th ACM International Systems and Software Product Line Conference Volume A*, ser. SPLC '22, Graz, Austria: Association for Computing Machinery, 2022, pp. 250–254, ISBN: 9781450394437. ODI: 10.1145/3546932.3547015.
- L. Marchezan, W. Assunção, J. Carbonell, E. Rodrigues, M. Bernardino, and F. Basso, "SPLReePlan Automated Support for Software Product Line Reengineering Planning," in 15th Brazilian Symposium on Software Components, Architectures, and Reuse, ser. SBCARS '21, Joinville, Brazil, 2021, pp. 1–10, ISBN: 9781450384193. 9 DOI: 10.1145/3483899.3483902.
- L. Marchezan, J. Carbonell, E. Rodrigues, M. Bernardino, F. P. Basso, and W. K. G. Assunção, "Enhancing the Feature Retrieval Process with Scoping and Tool Support: PAxSPL_v2," in *Proceedings of the 24th ACM International Systems and Software Product Line Conference Volume B*, ser. SPLC '20, Montreal, QC, Canada: Association for Computing Machinery, 2020, pp. 29–36, ISBN: 9781450375702.

 © DOI: 10.1145/3382026.3425767.
- L. Marchezan, G. Bolfe, E. Rodrigues, M. Bernardino, and F. P. Basso, "Thoth: A web-based tool to support systematic reviews," in 2019 ACM/IEEE International Symposium on Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement (ESEM), 2019, pp. 1–6. DOI: 10.1109/ESEM.2019.8870160.
- 9 L. Marchezan, E. Rodrigues, M. Bernardino, and F. P. Basso, "A customizable spl scoping process for spl reengineering," in *Anais da III Escola Regional de Engenharia de Software*, SBC, 2019, pp. 137–146.

- J. Carbonelli, L. Marchezan, A. Neto, E. Rodrigues, M. Bernardino, and Y. Lima, "Analyzing the impact of the search phase in a systematic mapping study," in *Anais da II Escola Regional de Engenharia de Software*, SBC, 2018, pp. 33–40.
- J. P. S. da Silva, M. Ecar, M. S. Pimenta, G. T. A. Guedes, L. P. Franz, and L. Marchezan, "A systematic literature review of uml-based domain-specific modeling languages for self-adaptive systems," in *Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Software Engineering for Adaptive and Self-Managing Systems*, ser. SEAMS '18, Gothenburg, Sweden: Association for Computing Machinery, 2018, pp. 87–93, ISBN: 9781450357159. ODI: 10.1145/3194133.3194136.
- L. Marchezan, E. Rodrigues, M. Bernardino, M. Laser, and F. Lima, "Towards a generic process for spl re-engineering," in *Anais da I Escola Regional de Engenharia de Software*, SBC, 2017, pp. 1–8.

Books and Chapters

- L. Marchezan, E. Rodrigues, J. Carbonell, M. Bernardino, F. P. Basso, and W. K. Assunção, "PAxSPL: A Framework for Aiding SPL Reengineering Planning," in *Handbook of Re-Engineering Software Intensive Systems into Software Product Lines*, Springer, 2022, pp. 319–353.
- E. M. Rodrigues, A. F. Zorzo, and L. Marchezan, "PLeTs: A Software Product Line for Testing Tools," in *UML-Based Software Product Line Engineering with SMarty*, Springer, 2022, pp. 315–334.

Skills

Languages	Strong reading, writing and speaking competencies for English and Portuguese.
C 1:	I D (C D (I WT V

Coding Java, Dart, PHP, C#, Python, LTEX.

Databases Cloud Firestore, Mysql, Postgresql.

Web Dev JavaScript, HTML, css, Apache Web Server, Tomcat Web Server.

Modeling. UML, Feature models, ER.

Technologies GitHub, Bitbucket, Jira, Laravel, Flutter, Firebase, Eclipse Modeling Fraemework.

Misc. Academic research, teaching, LaTeX typesetting and publishing.

Miscellaneous Experience

Reviews for Journals

2022 Journal of Software: Evolution and Process

2023 Journal of Systems and Software

Awards and Achievements

- Best Paper Award, ICSSP/ICGSE 2022.
- 2021 Best Master Thesis, Software Engineering Doctoral and Master Theses Competition Brazil.
- Student with the most outstanding performance in the Software Engineering Masters Course, Universidade Federal do Pampa.
- Student with the most outstanding performance in the Software Engineering Undergraduate Course, Universidade Federal do Pampa.
- Student with the most outstanding performance in the Software Engineering Undergraduate Course, Universidade Federal do Pampa.
- 2014 **Dean's List Certificate**, Illinois Institute of Technology School of Applied Technology.

References

Available on Request